single sheet binding is a method used
for individual sheets of paper this
works for paper which is difficult to
fold into signatures like heavy paper
stock or printed sheets hey this is
another one of those tutorials you guys
have been requesting ever since I
started my channel and it's finally here
this stitching method works great for
thick sheets of paper but keep in mind
that if you use this method you will be
binding every single page so for those
of you who have hundreds of single
sheets to bind this might not be the
most efficient option but I do have some
other single sheet binding tutorials
which you can find in the video
description below and while you're there
you can find a complete list of supplies
that I will use to make this book to
start amusing 20 sheets of watercolor
paper even if your paper is thick and
you're concerned that the thread might
tear the binding holes an option is to
tape the edge you will be binding on
this step is optional and it's just
extra reinforcement I'm placing half of
the tape on one side and folding the
paper over pressing down on the other
side then trimming off the extra tape on
the ends and I'm going to repeat this on
each page you might find that a lot of
steps in this video take a while so I
just kind of like to zone out and listen
to a book while I make a book if you
guys also like to do this
audible is offering a free audiobook and
free 30-day trial membership just go to
audible.com slash C lemon if you're
interested in listening to an e-book
while you work you can also find a link
to audible.com slash C lemon in the
description below after taping all
twenty sheets now let's move on to the
binding holes on the top edge measure
out a half inch over and make three
marks that are 3/4 inch apart then do
the same on the bottom edge you can also
change the measurements it's really up
to you I usually find if they are closer
to the top and bottom of the edge the
pages won't be as loose or wiggle around
as
now use that sheet as a template to
pierce the holes through about four
sheets at a time for the cover I'm using
plane board which I saved from the back
of sketch pads if you need some ideas on
where you can find board check out this
video here following the same process
use the page as a template and Pierce
holes in the cover board make sure they
are large enough for the needle to go
through okay now let's bind this method
is a little different and requires
individual stitching for each station so
I'm using six pieces of wax thread one
for each station if you want to learn
how to wax your own thread check out
this video here to determine the length
is tomato long the area as many times as
there are pages then you will need a
binding needle for each station so six
in this case this may seem like a lot
but needles usually come in large packs
I prefer curved ones for this and if you
want to learn more info on book binding
needles check out this video here single
thread a needle with no knot it's easier
to bind this on the edge of a table
start with the bottom page and the back
cover and make sure you keep the rest of
the pages in the same order as you find
them on go through the first hole and
come back around to tie a knot right
next to it you can then trim off the end
and tuck it in then go around to the
covers first hole back out and through
the first loop you made make sure you go
under both threads when you come back
around throughout the rest of the
needles and repeat this step on the
remaining holes
here's that step one more time on the
third hole tie the knot on the sheet go
around to the cover
[Music]
and through the first loop you made you
might find that this method is a lot
like optics stitch binding so if you're
familiar with that this might come easy
to you when you have the first page done
bring on the next page loop around the
first hole back out and around the loop
you made do this with the remaining
holes on the page loop around and back
around repeat this step on the remaining
holes after the second page is done
place the third on and loop around the
first hole then you want to loop around
the previous stitch below it repeat that
for the remaining holes
[Music]
and repeat this step on the rest of the
pages always looping around the previous
stitch if you run out of thread it's no
problem just tie a knot on the loop cut
the thread off and you can tuck the end
under the loop then continue to the next
page with a new threaded needle and tie
it on just like you did in the beginning
go around the previous stitch cut the
excess off and tuck the end in and
continue binding in the same process
when you're done with the last page bind
on the cover much like you would a
regular sheet loop through the hole
around the previous stitch but this time
back around the stitch once more through
to the inside then tie a knot on the
inside thread tuck the end under and cut
the excess off repeat this on the rest
of the holes on the cover and try to
make the knobs close to the edge after
all that hard work it's finally finished
I hope this tutorial helps you out in
your next book project and if it does
give this video a thumbs up and let me
know how it goes in the comments below
for more book finding tutorials and DIY
projects be sure to subscribe to my
channel sea lemon if you are interested
in other single sheet methods check out
these videos here or see the links in
the description below don't forget to
follow me on my social links so we can
share project pictures
[Music]